so do you want to make a tactics game
like fire emblem final fantasy tactics
xcom this guy
battletech
or you are feeling a little nostalgic
for something like front mission or
you're truly the coolest man alive and
remember jagged alliance
all of those games share similar systems
between each other all of them use grid
map for movement some of them use hexis
instead of squares but overall it
functions the same in this series i will
be covering the way to make a tactical
combat game with some simulation aspects
of other titles
main aim is to make combat works then i
will build on top of it
as a main inspiration i will be using
fire emblem series of games mostly fire
emblem's 3 houses which i desperately
want to play but i don't own switch
so to be fair i'm mostly basing my
knowledge on youtube videos and fire
emblem games from 3ds and pass of
radiance but if you want to make xcom or
something else don't click away as i
said those games are very similar in
many aspects and it will be possible to
adapt what we are going to do to make
any other tactical game you want to make
this tutorial will use unity of version
and it should be workable on any other
versions later on with maybe slight
minor changes
we will be using urp as a main renderer
if you encounter any issues make sure to
first check the pinned comment
all people makes mistakes and i'm not an
exception if i make a mistake or need to
add a correction i will be posting the
correction in the pinned comment if
there is no pinned comment which helps
you leave your comment or join the
discord and i will try to help you as
much as i can
if you follow my channel you might know
that i already have a series dedicated
to grid map which we will be making in
this tutorial
yet in that series i were making 2d top
down grid map this series will be making
a 3d map
please leave a like and comment if you
like this series if you really want to
support me i have patreon in the
description and we have a nice compute
discord server where we can cheat chat
and share joy so join in the link in the
description
good let's go everyone stay strong
today we will begin with setting up the
grid remove readme file and let's begin
create an empty object and call it a
grid
create a new script called node
and create another new script called
grid
open node script because node will not
be a component remove mono monobehaviour
inheritance
every component like this grid is
derived from monobehaviour
so if you try to attach the node like
component to this grid object it will
not work
back to node script
declare one public bool variable called
possible which will mark the node as
being possible by character or not
now open grid script
so to define the space where our
character will be able to move we will
create a 2d array of nodes
now we need to define the size of the
grid space create two variables width
and length
of the map
actually let's make them serialized
fields
so you will be able to modify them in
the editor
on the start initiate the node array
let's make
some kind of area out of floor and few
boxes to represent playing field
good now we have a space to play around
open the grid script we need to describe
the size of each node in the world for
this we need to define the size of each
node create a serialized float variable
called cell size
now we want to visualize our grid in on
draw gizmos cycle through width and
length and using gizmo square draw the
nodes
calculate the position of the node in
the world space
draw the gizmo
now you can see the nodes on the scene
let's make them smaller
and if you move your grid object it will
change the point of origin of those
nodes
it will make adjusting the grid easier
when it needs to be done
now we have a grid visualized on the
scene but right now the grid itself
actually is not populated with actual
data
we are just using the size of the grid
to draw it on the scene
what we need to do is to populate the
grid with data based on the scene we
have created
to populate the grid with data about
possible terrain we want to block out
the impossible terrain
you see instead of selecting individual
nodes and assigning the real list that
this node is impossible to traverse you
can define that certain colliders on the
scene represent the area impossible to
move through
in our case it is simple just those
walls
let's move them to a new layer called
obstacle
what we will be doing now is detecting
is the node collides with obstacle if it
does mark it as an unpossible node
so on the start create and call generate
grid
initialize grid inside generate grid
instead of start
inside call and create a new method
called check possible terrain
cycle through this and length of the
grid
and here we want to use check box to
determine if the area is possible and
not obstructed by obstacles
first parameter will be a world position
we already have world position
calculation in the ondraw gizmos so to
not repeat ourselves let's extract it
into the method
the automatic extraction inverted the
parameters let's fix it
then we have a half extent of the cube
we will be projecting
simply divide the vector31 by half
because it is half extent of the cube
and multiply by the cell size
third parameter is the rotation of the
cube in quaternion simply pass
quaternion identity we don't need any
angle here
last fourth parameter will be our layer
mask where we can pass the layer of our
obstacles
create serialized variable for this
layer
layer allow us to ignore all other
colliders which is not obstacles for
determining is this not possible or not
now we want to visualize possible and
impossible notes
in the on draw gizmo create exit gate
easy grid is null
so gizmos will not be drawn if the grid
is not initiated yet
then check if the grid node in position
possible make it white otherwise red
now before we proceed we have determined
if the area for the node is possible but
we haven't assigned this state to the
grid initiate the node and assign
possible value
in the editor assign the obstacle layer
and launch the game
this error is happening because when we
are checking the box it return true if
it collides with something
in that case it returns true
which in our case should be inverted
because our variable is called possible
not an impossible
and now our grid is easily scalable and
easily changeable
you just need to move objects with an
obstacle layer
good this is a good stopping point for
tonight if you have any questions or any
ideas about code please leave your
comment below if you are interested in
seeing what will come out of this please
subscribe if you want to support further
you can find my patreon in the
description special thank you to andrew
b long for his generous support
with best regards see in the next
episode
you